<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Blog Name</title>
  <subtitle>Blog subtitle</subtitle>
  <id>http://blog.url.com/blog</id>
  <link href="http://blog.url.com/blog"/>
  <link href="http://blog.url.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <updated>2016-06-27T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Blog Author</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>36...Or More Hours in Chiang Mai</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/blog/2016/06/36-or-more-hours-in-chiang-mai/"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/blog/2016/06/36-or-more-hours-in-chiang-mai/</id>
    <published>2016-06-27T00:00:00-05:00</published>
    <updated>2016-07-23T16:17:28-05:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Ah, Chiang Mai. How do I love thee? You are earthen and sacred, dusted in dew and crowned with nature. Maybe that's why you're a &lt;a href="http://www.businessinsider.com/ten-places-to-go-if-world-goes-to-crap-2009-10?op=1" target="_blank" title="top place to go if the world goes to hell"&gt;top place to go if the world goes to hell&lt;/a&gt;, but hell, you're a haven on the world's best of days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/201607-36-hours/walking-street-2.jpg" alt="soap flowers at chiang mai night bazaar" class="banner" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Soap flowers at the Chiang Mai night bazaar&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-typical-fare"&gt;The Typical Fare&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The classic guide books would march you through &lt;a href="https://www.tripadvisor.com/Attraction_Review-g7702231-d447417-Reviews-Umbrella_Village_Bor_Sang-Bo_Sang_San_Kamphaeng.html" target="_blank" title="umbrella factories"&gt;umbrella factories&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.tripadvisor.com/Travel-g293917-c127870/Chiang-Mai:Thailand:Elephant.Camps.Chiang.Mai.html" target="_blank" title="elephant camps"&gt;elephant camps&lt;/a&gt; before busing you to a &lt;a href="http://www.lonelyplanet.com/thailand/chiang-mai-province/chiang-mai/activities/food-drink/traditional-khantoke-dinner-show-chiang-mai" target="_blank" title="Kantoke cultural show"&gt;Kantoke cultural show&lt;/a&gt; and then dropping you off at the &lt;a href="https://www.tripadvisor.com/Attraction_Review-g293917-d447327-Reviews-Night_Bazaar-Chiang_Mai.html" target="_blank" title="night bazaar"&gt;night bazaar&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don't get me wrong, all of those things are great. They will make you fall in love with this city like it's a hot girl on a magazine in the checkout aisle. But I love this city like it's a book I'll never finish and I've gone to bed with every night. I've explored its every avenue, savored its every delicious twist and turn, and still it never ceases to amaze me. That love is what I want to share  with you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/201607-36-hours/wororot-2.jpg" alt="florescent signs illuminate dried fruit and spices at warorot market" class="banner" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Florescent signs illuminate dried fruit and spices at Warorot market&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="day-1-market--river"&gt;Day 1: Market &amp;amp; River&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h4 id="morning-at-the-market"&gt;Morning at the Market&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Start your day at &lt;a href="https://migrationology.com/warorot-market-chiang-mai/" target="_blank" title="Warorot market"&gt;Warorot market&lt;/a&gt;, entering from Kuang Men Road just off Tapae Road. Browse the textiles and plastics before venturing into the 3-story mecca of dried foods, spices, housewares, fireworks, and school uniforms that is Warorot proper. Continue weaving your way toward the river and past the vendor selling delicious fried insects before coming out at the flower market which lines both sides of Praisanee Road.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="lunch--treats"&gt;Lunch &amp;amp; Treats&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Use your last burst of energy to cross the Nawarat bridge and stagger into &lt;a href="https://www.tripadvisor.com/ShowUserReviews-g293917-d878209-r145023668-Wawee_Coffee-Chiang_Mai.html" target="_blank" title="Wawee Coffee"&gt;Wawee Coffee&lt;/a&gt; for a refreshing iced drink and river view. If you're ready for lunch, jump on a songtaew going north and get off at &lt;a href="http://eatingtheglobe.com/favorite-khao-soi-chiang-mai/" target="_blank" title="Khao Soi Lam Duan"&gt;Khao Soi Lam Duan&lt;/a&gt; for an authentic bowl of &lt;i&gt;khao soi&lt;/i&gt;: soft and crispy noodles in a curry broth and topped with pickled vegetables. If you prefer more familiar fare, skip the songtaew and weave through the back streets to &lt;a href="https://www.tripadvisor.com/Restaurant_Review-g293917-d1081063-Reviews-Bake_and_Bite-Chiang_Mai.html" target="_blank" title="Bake n' Bite"&gt;Bake n' Bite&lt;/a&gt; for cafe-style breakfasts and sandwiches.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After lunch, follow Charoen Rat on foot to browse any art galleries that are open and end up at &lt;a href="http://www.vjoteahouse.com/" target="_blank" title="Vieng Joom On Tea House"&gt;Vieng Joom On Tea House&lt;/a&gt; for an afternoon refreshment on their gorgeous, billowy patio. If you have it in you, song taew or tuk tuk a few minutes south to &lt;a href="http://chiangmai-artinparadise.com/" target="_blank" title="Art in Paradise"&gt;Art in Paradise&lt;/a&gt;, an interactive art exhibit of 3-dimensional optical illusions painted to serve as photo backdrops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, any normal person should be sweaty and exhausted and ready for a quick cool off at their hotel before venturing back out for dinner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="dinner--shopping"&gt;Dinner &amp;amp; Shopping&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Return to the river area around dinnertime to dine  at either&lt;a href="http://wherestheduke.com" target="_blank" title="The Duke's"&gt;The Duke's&lt;/a&gt; for indulgent, delicious American good or aboard the river "cruise" that leaves from the &lt;a href="http://www.theriversidechiangmai.com/4-1-nightly_cruise.php" target="_blank" title="Riverside"&gt;Riverside&lt;/a&gt; every night at 8. Cruisegoers may want to stop in or call ahead since the cruise is in fact just a riverboat that seats maybe 40.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After dinner, go ahead and head to the super touristy &lt;a href="http://www.1stopchiangmai.com/shopping/night_market" target="_blank" title="night bazaar"&gt;night bazaar&lt;/a&gt;; no trip to Chiang Mai is complete without it. You can walk the 15 minutes if you're so inclined, or tuk tuks and song taews should be ubiquitous. Don't feel obligated to shut it down; do stay long enough to enjoy banana roti from the stall that's in front of McDonald's.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/201607-36-hours/buddhas.jpg" alt="buddha statues sit in a row at wat prathat doi suthep" class="banner" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Buddha statues sit in a row at Wat Phra That Doi Suthep&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="day-2-nimman--cmu"&gt;Day 2: Nimman &amp;amp; CMU&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h4 id="breakfast--lunch"&gt;Breakfast &amp;amp; Lunch&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Start your day on the north end of Nimman at &lt;a href="http://www.ristr8to-coffee-chiangmai.com/" target="_blank" title="Ristr8o"&gt;Ristr8o&lt;/a&gt; for a coffee snob-approved single origin latte and award-winning &lt;a href="https://www.instagram.com/ristr8to/" target="_blank" title="latte art"&gt;latte artist&lt;/a&gt; Arnon Thitprasert &lt;i&gt;or&lt;/i&gt; hit up its nearby younger brother, the experimental &lt;a href="http://bk.asia-city.com/travel/news/ristr8to-now-has-spin" target="_blank" title="Ristr8to Lab"&gt;Ristr8to Lab&lt;/a&gt;. Next, head 1 block north to &lt;a href="http://www.nimmansoi1.com/" target="_blank" title="Nimman Soi 1"&gt;Nimman Soi 1&lt;/a&gt;, a street known for trendy boutiques and craft textiles. Then, circle back and stop in at &lt;a href="https://www.facebook.com/guufusionrotiandtea/" target="_blank" title="Guu Fusion Roti and Tea"&gt;Guu Fusion Roti and Tea&lt;/a&gt; for a mid-morning fix of flaky fried dough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Afterward, make your way west along Nimmanhaemin proper and stop in at some of the boutiques along the way, such as Chabaa (bohemian apparel) or Pink Pussy (loud and proud outrageous jewelry). Arrive for lunch at &lt;a href="http://www.thesaladconcept.com/about.php" target="_blank" title="Salad Concept"&gt;Salad Concept&lt;/a&gt;, before exploring the current exhibit at &lt;a href="http://www.sangdeegallery.org/" target="_blank" title="Sangdee Cafe and Art Gallery"&gt;Sangdee Cafe and Art Gallery&lt;/a&gt;. Continue weaving through back streets to find &lt;a href="http://tableforthreeplease.com/2011/01/chiang-mai-iberry-garden/" target="_blank" title="iBerry"&gt;iBerry&lt;/a&gt; for exotic ice cream flavors (spicy mango? salty pomelo?) and a photoshoot in their surrealist garden (designed by its founder comedian Nate Udom) that was basically made to be instagrammed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you actually expect to relax on vacation, head next to one of the many nail salons or spas in the area and rejoin the itinerary later. Otherwise, continue on to the CMU area and up Doi Suthep.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="afternoon-up-the-mountain"&gt;Afternoon Up the Mountain&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take a moto or songtaew the 20 minutes up Doi Suthep, the mountain just north of town. Pitstop at the &lt;a href="http://www.thiswaytoparadise.com/chiang-mai-wat-phrathat-doi-suthep-huay-kaew-waterfall/" target="_blank" title="Huay Gaew waterfall"&gt;Huay Gaew waterfall&lt;/a&gt; before continuing to &lt;a href="http://www.lonelyplanet.com/thailand/chiang-mai-province/chiang-mai/sights/religious/wat-phra-that-doi-suthep" target="_blank" title="Wat Phra That Doi Suthep"&gt;Wat Phra That Doi Suthep&lt;/a&gt;, a once-sacred temple that is now equal parts place of worship and tourist attraction. As tourists, expect to sweat your way up 309 steps and then shell out a small entrance fee. Afterwards, if you're still enjoying the muggy mountain air, you may choose to visit the unfortunately-named &lt;a href="https://www.tripadvisor.com/Attraction_Review-g293917-d1760058-Reviews-Bhubing_Palace-Chiang_Mai.html" target="_blank" title="Bhubing Palace"&gt;Bhubing Palace&lt;/a&gt;, a royal palace with impressive rose gardens, but be warned that they have strict rules against shorts, short skirts, and sleeveless tops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="dinner--dessert"&gt;Dinner &amp;amp; Dessert&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the evening, head toward Chiang Mai University for a sit or stroll in the park by the &lt;a href="https://www.tripadvisor.com/Attraction_Review-g293917-d8826313-Reviews-Ang_Kaew_Reservoir-Chiang_Mai.html" tartget="_blank" title="reservoir"&gt;reservoir&lt;/a&gt; on campus. Then, walk across the street to the &lt;a href="http://www.paperplanesblog.com/student-market/" target="_blank" title="university night market"&gt;university night market&lt;/a&gt;, which favors hipster and anime kitch over the touristy knick knacks you'll find elsewhere. Grab dinner in the outdoor food court, such as &lt;i&gt;moo ga ta&lt;/i&gt;, or meat cooked yourself on a tabletop grill. End the night back on Nimman at &lt;a href="http://www.mont-nomsod.com/home.html" title="Mont Nom Sod"&gt;Mont Nom Sod&lt;/a&gt; (มนต์ นมสด) which led the trend in fancy toast and flavored milk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/201607-36-hours/cooking-class.jpg" alt="aspiring chef makes big flame in wok during thai cooking class" class="banner" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class="caption"&gt;An aspiring chef makes a big flame in a wok during a Thai cooking class&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="day-3-tapae"&gt;Day 3: Tapae&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h4 id="coffee--class"&gt;Coffee &amp;amp; Class&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Get an early start at one of &lt;a href="http://www.paperplanesblog.com/50-of-the-best-cafes-in-chiang-mai/" target="_blank" title="Chiang Mai's best coffee shops"&gt;Chiang Mai's best coffee shops&lt;/a&gt;; the quality-obsessed &lt;a href="https://www.facebook.com/ponganesespressobar/" target="_blank" title="Ponganese"&gt;Ponganese&lt;/a&gt; or the social enterprise &lt;a href="http://www.akhaama.com/" target="_blank" title="Akha Ama"&gt;Akha Ama&lt;/a&gt; are both good choices. Then spend your day at a cooking class, like one offered by &lt;a href="https://www.tripadvisor.com/Attraction_Review-g293917-d1115891-Reviews-Chiang_Mai_Thai_Cookery_School-Chiang_Mai.html" target="_blank" title="Chiang Mai Thai Cookery School"&gt;Chiang Mai Thai Cookery School&lt;/a&gt;. (While not the cheapest option, in my opinions, this is one of the best. Other options abound; any will be entertaining and perhaps even educational.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If cooking is not your thing, consider a 1-day massage class or fruit carving class. For the adrenaline junkie, consider trekking, &lt;a href="http://www.thailandclimbing.com/climb-crazy-horse/" target="_blank" title="rock climbing"&gt;rock climbing&lt;/a&gt;, or &lt;a href="https://www.treetopasia.com/thailand-holiday/chiang-mai" target="_blank" title="zip-lining through the jungle"&gt;zip-lining through the jungle&lt;/a&gt;. Any travel agent in the Tapae area can make a booking for you and prices typically range from $20-60 for a 1-day activity. Advanced bookings are helpful but day-of is possible if you get an early start.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you find yourself with time in the Tapae area, you'll notice &lt;i&gt;wats&lt;/i&gt;, or temples, on just about every corner. Within the old city, a one square mile area surrounded by a moat, are more temples than you could see in a day, most of which you can simply walk in to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="dinner--drinks"&gt;Dinner &amp;amp; Drinks&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;End your day at the chichi &lt;a href="https://www.tripadvisor.com/Restaurant_Review-g293917-d3715658-Reviews-Ginger_Kafe-Chiang_Mai.html" target="_blank" title="Ginger &amp;amp; Cafe"&gt;Ginger &amp;amp; Cafe&lt;/a&gt; for exquite food and dinks or, for a more casual option, consider checking out &lt;a href="http://dashteakhouse.com/" target="_blank" title="Dash"&gt;Dash&lt;/a&gt;. Afterward, hop on a songtaew or walk the mile-ish to &lt;a href="https://www.tripadvisor.com/Restaurant_Review-g293917-d3743573-Reviews-The_North_Gate_Jazz_Club-Chiang_Mai.html" target="_blank" title="North Gate Jazz"&gt;North Gate Jazz&lt;/a&gt;, a hole in the wall hopping jazz club that is beloved by Thais and tourists alike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/201607-36-hours/walking-street-3.jpg" alt="tribal clothes and accessories make an appearance at sunday night walking street" class="banner" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Fisherman pants and Thai tribal handiwork make appearances at Sunday night walking street&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="thursday--sunday"&gt;Thursday &amp;amp; Sunday&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If your trip affords you the opportunity, mingle with an eclectic expat crowd upstairs at the &lt;a href="http://www.unirishpub.com/" target="_blank" title="UN Irish Pub"&gt;UN Irish Pub&lt;/a&gt; pub quiz every Thursday night.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do everything you can to experience the hustle and bustle of &lt;a href="https://www.tripadvisor.com/Attraction_Review-g1308496-d945764-Reviews-Sunday_Night_Market_Walking_Street_Tha_Pae_Gate-Chiang_Mai_Province.html" target="_blank" title="Sunday night walking street"&gt;Sunday night walking street&lt;/a&gt;. Beat the rush by starting promptly at 5pm, but don't be surprised when foot traffic slows to a crawl around 8. Shop from local artists and craftspeople, many of whom may do this as a side gig, and enjoy the full range of available street food. When pedestrians freeze in their tracks at 6pm, you're not being punked; it's a moment of respect paid twice daily during a broadcast of the national anthem. You should follow suit. Once you've shopped till you dropped, don't be ashamed to take refuge in a foot massage before squeezing in just a &lt;i&gt;liiiittle more.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/201607-36-hours/elephants-2.jpg" alt="mother and baby elephant at an elephant camp near chiang mai" class="banner" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class="caption"&gt;Mother and baby elephant at an elephant camp near Chiang Mai&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="get-out-of-town"&gt;Get Out of Town&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h4 id="north-samoeng-loop-12-day"&gt;North Samoeng Loop (1/2 Day)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Best tackled with your own transportation or a day-long songtaew hire.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Start mid morning with a drive through the mountains to arrive at &lt;a href="https://www.tripadvisor.com/Attraction_Review-g1766192-d4322964-Reviews-Doi_Mon_Cham-Mae_Rim.html" target="_blank" title="Doi Mon Chaem and the Nong Hoi Royal Project"&gt;Doi Mon Chaem and the Nong Hoi Royal Project&lt;/a&gt; in time for lunch in a hut overlooking a luscious fertile valley. If you haven't already overdosed on gardens, return by way of the &lt;a href="https://www.tripadvisor.com/Attraction_Review-g1766192-d548427-Reviews-Queen_Sirikit_Botanic_Garden-Mae_Rim.html" target="_blank" title="Queen Sirikit Botanical Gardens"&gt;Queen Sirikit Botanical Gardens&lt;/a&gt;. Afterwards, stop off in Mae Rim at &lt;a href="https://www.tripadvisor.com/LocationPhotoDirectLink-g1766192-d3946130-i88121884-Wawee_Coffee-Mae_Rim.html" target="_blank" title="Suan Lahu Cafe' @ Tita Gallery"&gt;Suan Lahu Cafe' @ Tita Gallery&lt;/a&gt;, a serene, tucked-away art gallery and coffee shop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="northeast-nature-1-day"&gt;Northeast Nature (1 Day)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Best tackled with your own transportation or a day-long songtaew hire.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Head northeast from Chiang Mai and pick up a &lt;i&gt;som tam&lt;/i&gt; picnic on the way to &lt;a href="http://tielandtothailand.com/bua-tong-sticky-waterfalls-chiang-mai/" target="_blank" title="Bua Tong Waterfall and Chet Si Spring"&gt;Bua Tong Waterfall and Chet Si Spring&lt;/a&gt;. This waterfall's limestone surface means you can climb up and down it spiderman-style and gives it its English moniker &lt;i&gt;sticky falls&lt;/i&gt;. Next, head to the &lt;a href="http://tielandtothailand.com/mae-ngat-dam-floating-houses-chiang-mai/" target="_blank" title="Mae Ngat Dam"&gt;Mae Ngat Dam&lt;/a&gt; and rent a houseboat for the day. Docks allow for swimming, jumping and sunbathing; the park also offers a full-service restaurant and the option to stay overnight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="city-south-12-day"&gt;City South (1/2 Day)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;With the exception of Wat Doi Kam, most of these places are more or less accessible by public transportation.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spend an afternoon at &lt;a href="https://www.tripadvisor.com/Attraction_Review-g293917-d1699367-Reviews-Central_Airport_Plaza-Chiang_Mai.html" target="_blank" title="Central Airport Plaza"&gt;Central Airport Plaza&lt;/a&gt;, just one of many modern malls in Chiang Mai, but be sure to check out the Northern Village area which boast all the best food and wares from markets around town, but in the bliss of air conditioned comfort. From there, you can drive to the top (or walk from the base) of &lt;a href="https://www.tripadvisor.com/Attraction_Review-g293917-d1754563-Reviews-Wat_Phra_That_Doi_Kham_Temple_of_the_Golden_Mountain-Chiang_Mai.html" target="_blank"&gt;Wat Doi Kham&lt;/a&gt; just before sunset to enjoy a quiet temple and stunning views pretty much all to yourself. Drive down the mountain to dine among jungle plants and water features at &lt;a href="https://www.tripadvisor.com/Restaurant_Review-g293917-d2659338-Reviews-Khaomao_Khaofang_Restaurant-Chiang_Mai.html" target="_blank" title="Kao Mao Kao Fang"&gt;Kao Mao Kao Fang&lt;/a&gt;. Finally, end the day at the &lt;a href="http://www.chiangmainightsafari.com/" target="_blank" title="Night Safari"&gt;Night Safari&lt;/a&gt;, for an impressive noctural animal display. Unless, of course, you've been to its rival in Singapore, in which case you should prepare to be disappointed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="elephant-conservation-center-12-day-or-more"&gt;Elephant Conservation Center (1/2 Day or more)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It might be cliche, but by all means &lt;i&gt;do&lt;/i&gt; go see elephants on your trip. Any number of tours exist that will take you to any number of elephant camps, which are a confusing combination of camp-as-in-summer-camp and camp-as-in-internment-camp. I really don't know and I've been to &lt;i&gt;all of them&lt;/i&gt;. Many times. I hear good things about the &lt;a href="http://www.thailandelephant.org/en/index.html" target="_blank" title="Thai Elephant Conservation Center"&gt;Thai Elephant Conservation Center&lt;/a&gt;, which also offers homestays and multiday mahout training experiences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="doi-inthanon-12-day-or-more"&gt;Doi Inthanon (1/2 Day or more)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;This mountainous drive is best tackled with a rental car, hired van, or on a tour.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Drive up Thailand's tallest mountain &lt;a href="https://www.thainationalparks.com/doi-inthanon-national-park" target="_blank" title="Doi Inthanon"&gt;Doi Inthanon&lt;/a&gt; for a chance to feel–believe it or not–a brisk chill. Drink hot cocoa at the top of the mountain, walk through a jungle boardwalk, and detour by myriad waterfalls. You can detour by the &lt;a href="http://www.tourismthailand.org/Attraction/Doi-Inthanon-Royal-Project--159" target="_blank" title="Doi Inthanon Royal Project"&gt;Doi Inthanon Royal Project&lt;/a&gt;, including extensive gardens, agricultural projects, and several &lt;a href="http://www.royal-inthanon.com/Club/House" target="blank" title="Doi Inthanon Bungalows"&gt;bungalows&lt;/a&gt; where you can stay overnight. &lt;a href="http://www.adventureinyou.com/everything-you-need-to-know-about-camping-at-doi-inthanon-national-park/" target="_blank" title="Doi Inthanon Camping"&gt;Camping opportunities&lt;/a&gt;, including gear rental, also exist for the more intrepid travellers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="pai-2-3-days"&gt;Pai (2-3 Days)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;A three-hour bus ride departs from the main bus stations multiple times daily.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The road from Chiang Mai to &lt;a href="http://www.lonelyplanet.com/thailand/mae-hong-son-province/pai/introduction" target="_blank" title="Pai"&gt;Pai&lt;/a&gt; is known for its 762 curves as you weave through mountains to arrive at this hippy haven. Go trekking or tubing, or savor the slower pace of life, coffee shops and art scene.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="map"&gt;Map&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;iframe src="https://www.google.com/maps/d/u/0/embed?mid=1HhEUhD1tCM36mG3TBSnegYd1WZ4" width="640" height="480" class=""&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Getting Started with Middleman</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/blog/2016/06/getting-started-with-middleman/"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/blog/2016/06/getting-started-with-middleman/</id>
    <published>2016-06-26T00:00:00-05:00</published>
    <updated>2016-06-26T23:20:18-05:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Hello blogland!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much like the shoemaker's children go barefoot, the web developer's personal site often suffers neglect. Wanting a blogging platform for pragmatic reasons, I knew I couldn't live with myself if I built yet another &lt;em&gt;*gasp*&lt;/em&gt; Wordpress site. Having recently joined the cult of static site fanaticism, and curious about this one called Middleman, I present to you a fun Sunday evening project for weirdos and normals alike: how to create a Middleman blog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As is often the case with these things, each install is going to require a slightly different subset of these steps, depending on your setup and what you do or do not already have configured on your machine. As is also often the case, you're going to get frustrated and I'm going to sound like a jerk when I fail to tell you to update homebrew. Again. Or whatever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here's the general outline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Install/update Ruby&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Install Middleman&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Initialize a Middleman site&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Add blog functionality&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Enhance blog features&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Move blog to subdirectory&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Voila! Done.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id="installupdate-ruby"&gt;Install/Update Ruby&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I'm running a mac, so I pretty much googled &lt;a href="http://code.tutsplus.com/tutorials/how-to-install-ruby-on-a-mac--net-21664" target="_blank"&gt;How to Install Ruby on a Mac&lt;/a&gt; and followed this article.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;About halfway though, it has you update your bash profile. If you haven't already tricked out your bash profile, I highly recommend doing so. I usually start with &lt;a href="https://natelandau.com/my-mac-osx-bash_profile/" target="_blank"&gt;Nate Landeau's bash profile&lt;/a&gt; and then make it my own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you're still following the Tutsplus tutorial, you can stop after Step 3. Everything about XCode and Rails and versioning are really specific to the use case and not necessary for a basic Middleman build. For what it's worth, I'm running Ruby 2.3.0 but that information will be obsolete in about 5 seconds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="install-middleman"&gt;Install Middleman&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From there, I jumped over to the &lt;a href="https://middlemanapp.com/" target="_blank"&gt;Middleman&lt;/a&gt; site and followed their instructions. To start with you'll open your terminal and run:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;gem install middleman&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;which installs the Middleman Ruby gem on your system. Now, you're able to use the &lt;code&gt;middleman&lt;/code&gt; prompt to create any number of Middleman sites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="initialize-a-middleman-site"&gt;Initialize a Middleman site&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, cd into whatever folder where you want to make your site. For me this means:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;cd /Users/USERNAME/Sites&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then run this command to create your new site in a folder called &lt;em&gt;my_site&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;middleman init my_site&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the time of this writing, I got prompts asking if I wanted to activate livereload and compass and the answer is yes and yes! Technically, you don't &lt;em&gt;have&lt;/em&gt; to, but then you'll miss out on all kinds of fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now you should see that a folder was created containing a source folder, a gemfile, and &lt;em&gt;config.rb&lt;/em&gt; file. This means your basic site is up and running, so to see it you'll run:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;bundle exec middleman server&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then visit http://localhost:4567/.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you just want a static site, you're done! Stop reading!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="add-blog-functionality"&gt;Add blog functionality&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is where the &lt;a href="https://middlemanapp.com/basics/blogging/" target="_blank"&gt;middleman documentation&lt;/a&gt; forks a bit and it took some experimentation. You have to decide whether you want to create a new blog site, retrofit your static site with a blog, or some other combination of roundabout problem solving which is what I did. And thank goodness! Middleman documentation isn't totally clear, so I'm going to save you some grief.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We're actually going to create a new site for the blog and then port over some of the features from our static site. At this time, the blog starter doesn't offer livereload and some of the features that the static starter does.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, we need to add the Middleman blog gem:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;gem install middleman-blog&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, navigate out of your &lt;em&gt;my_site&lt;/em&gt; folder and let's create a &lt;em&gt;my_blog&lt;/em&gt; site:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;middleman init my_blog --template=blog&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now move into the folder:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;cd my_blog&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And run:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;bundle exec middleman server&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now when you visit http://localhost:4567/, you should see an unstyled blog home page with one example post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="enhance-blog-features"&gt;Enhance blog features&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We're going to take all the goodness from the static site you created and marry it with the blog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, copy over all files from the source folder in &lt;em&gt;my_site&lt;/em&gt; into the source folder in &lt;em&gt;my_blog&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;except&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;index.html.erb&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, copy over these lines from the gemfile in &lt;em&gt;my_site&lt;/em&gt; and paste them into the gemfile in &lt;em&gt;my_blog&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;
gem 'middleman-livereload'
gem 'middleman-compass', '&amp;gt;= 4.0.0'
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, in the terminal, run:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;gem install middleman-livereload &amp;amp;&amp;amp; gem install middleman-compass&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, from &lt;em&gt;config.rb&lt;/em&gt;, copy over the code that activates livereload. It should look something like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;
configure :development do
  activate :livereload
end
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, grab the code from the layout.erb file in &lt;em&gt;my_site&lt;/em&gt; (this one is nested in the layouts folder) that references the font, stylesheet, and javascript and add it to the layout.erb file in &lt;em&gt;my_blog&lt;/em&gt;. It should look like this, but obviously you can customize those later:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;
&amp;lt;link href='//fonts.googleapis.com/css?family=Lato:300,400' rel='stylesheet' type='text/css'&amp;gt;

&amp;lt;%= stylesheet_link_tag :site %&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;%= javascript_include_tag :all %&amp;gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This step can be a little convoluted, but by comparing these two sites, you can learn a lot about what their disparate components do. Ideally by the end of this stage, your blog should be loading like it was at the end of the previous step, but now with some basic styles and livereload.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="move-blog-to-subdirectory"&gt;Move blog to subdirectory&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This may not apply to you, but I wanted my blog to live under /blog instead of in the root folder. This takes moving files and also customizing settings in config.rb.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, create your /blog subdirectory move the following files to it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;calendar.html.erb&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;index.html.erb&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;tag.html.erb&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;example post file&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we need to to update config.rb to reflect that we want the blog to serve from /blog. Update these three lines as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;
# Set blog home to live at /blog
blog.prefix = "blog"
	
# Set tag and calendar home to live at /blog/tags and /blog/date
blog.tag_template = "blog/tag.html"
blog.calendar_template = "blog/calendar.html"
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, we need to maintain separate &lt;a href="https://middlemanapp.com/basics/layouts/" target="_blank"&gt;layout files&lt;/a&gt; for our blog pages and our non-blog pages. Thankfully, we have both layout files already created from earlier steps. We just have to rename and rearrange them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, find the &lt;em&gt;layout.erb&lt;/em&gt; file that's in the root folder and rename it to &lt;em&gt;blog.erb&lt;/em&gt;. Then move it into the &lt;em&gt;layouts&lt;/em&gt; folder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, we're going to add this line to config.rb, which tells Middleman to use the blog.erb file as the layout for all pages in the /blog subdirectory:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;page "/blog/*", layout: :blog&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that your blog should be serving from /blog, your homepage may look pretty empty. Feel free to grab the index.html.erb from &lt;em&gt;my_site&lt;/em&gt; and copy to &lt;em&gt;my_blog&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now you should have a static page serving from http://localhost:4567/ and your blog homepage serving from http://localhost:4567/blog. You're ready to start writing!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="optional-customization"&gt;Optional Customization&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I chose to also add features including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;custom permalinks&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://middlemanapp.com/basics/blogging/#article-summaries" target="_blank"&gt;summaries&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;header and footer &lt;a href="https://middlemanapp.com/basics/partials/" target="_blank"&gt;partials&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;css and javascript minification&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of these are settings in config.rb. Others are pretty well documented already in the &lt;a href="https://middlemanapp.com/basics/install/" target="_blank"&gt;Middleman docs&lt;/a&gt; so I don't need to dive into them here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I'm just getting start with Middleman, but so far I'm pretty impressed with the ease of use plus extensibility. The documentation also feels really complete and generally easy to follow, so I was suprised at the gaps I found which prompted this post. Hopefully your experience has been even smoother and you're up and running without a hitch!&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
